Finding Aid for the Otto Kinkeldey Papers, 1898-1962
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
- Transcriptions by Kinkeldey, circa 1900-1940, IX.; Folder 73-146
  - Luzzaschi, Luzzasco, d. 1607 Beilage VI: Luzzaschi, undated, 3 pages of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript music. Pages numbered 17-19. For six unspecified instruments. The piece may be lacking its opening measures and it cannot be identified as a work by Luzzaschi. The title information is taken from a fragment of a wrapper. (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Luzzaschi, Luzzasco, d. 1607 Madrigali per cantare et sonare. Selections Madrigali per cantare et sonare, Roma 1601, undated, 32 pages of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. For one, two, or three sopranos and keyboard accompaniment. Contained on pages 286-295 of Kinkeldey's Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts. (Box 4, Folder 120)
    Aura soave -- O primavera -- Ch'io non t'ami -- Stral pungente d'amore -- Deh vieni ormai -- I' mi son giovinetta -- T'amo mia vita.
  - Malvezzi, Cristofano, 1547-1599 Intermedii et concerti, fatti per la commedia rappresentata in Firenze. Selections I Two works from the intermedi for the marriage of Ferdinando Medici and Christine of Lorraine in 1589, undated, 6 pages of manuscript music; 24 x 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Originally published in Venice by G. Vicenti, 1591. The edition was edited by Malvezzi, who also contributed music. (Box 4, Folder 121)
    Secondo intermedio. Sinfonia [for five instruments] / Luca Marenzio -- Primo intermedio. Dalle più alte sfere [transcribed as voice and accompaniment in keyboard reduction] / Antonio Archilei [possibly by Emilio de Cavalieri]
    Contained on pages 306-312 of Kinkeldey's Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts.
  - Mazzone, Marc'Antonio, fl. 1569-1593 Primo libro delle Magnificat. Selections Primo libro delle Magnificat composto da Don Marc'Antoniio Mazzone di Miglionico. In nouvo stile corrente, et commodo non solo ..., undated, 4 pages of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Originally published Venice: A. Gardane, 1593. Transcription on four staves with text. (Box 4, Folder 122)
    Ave maris stella -- Magnificat primo toni (Anima dea).
  - Melli, Domenico Maria, b. 1572 Musiche. Selections Le primo musiche el Signor Domenico Maria Melli ... Veneta ... 1609. 18 Stücke für 1 Stimme mit unbezifferten Bass, undated, 8 pages of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Title of Le Seconde Musiche transcribed on page 7. (Box 4, Folder 123)
    Primo Musiche. No. 1. Arde il cor e non chiede a l'ardor suo; No. 2. S'a la gelata mia timida lingua; No. 15. Fu cosi grave il duolo mio -- Seconde Musiche. No. 1. Languisco e moro, ahi cruda
  - Milán, Luis, 16th cent. Maestro. Selections Libro de musica de vihuela de mano. Intitulado. El Maestro ... Compuesto por don Luys Milan, undated, 22 pages of manuscript text and music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcription of portions of the text, a drawing of the instrument, and four of the fantasias in the original tablature. Originally issued 1536. (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Newsidler, Hans, 1508-1563 Newgeordent kunstlich Lautenbuch. Selections Miscellanea aus Ein newgeordent künstlich Lautenbuch, Hans Neusidler, Luturisten und Bürger zur Nürnberg, 1536, undated, 19 pages of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcriptions on two-stave keyboard format. (Box 4, Folder 125)
    Theil II. No. IX (fol. D II): Tus Biens / Ghiselin -- Theil II. No. X (Fol. D III v): Ein gut triu mit schönen fugen -- Theil I (Fol. s III): Preambel [1] -- [Theil I.] (Fol. s III v): Preambel [2] -- [Theil I.] (Fol. s IIII): Preambel [3] -- Preambel (fol. IIII v.) -- Ein gut Preambel (fol. X III) -- Theil II. [No.] I (fol. A III): Ein sehr guter organistischer preambel-- Theil II. No. XIX (Fol. H I v): Juli amors / Ghiselin -- [Theil II. No.] XX (fol. H IIII): Si sumpsero / Obrecht.
  - Nivers, Guillaume-Gabriel, 1632-1714 Livre d'orgue, no. 1. Selections Livre d'orgue conten. 100 pièces de tous les tons de l'eglise, Paris 1665 chez Ballard, Paris Bibl. Nat. Vm 1416, undated, 1 page of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. (Box 4, Folder 126)
    Prelude du 1 ton (page 1) -- Fugue (page 2) -- Diminution de la basse (page 3).
  - Piero, Maestro, fl. 1340-1350 Selections Two works by Magister Piero, undated, 7 pages of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcribed from the manuscript Biblioteca Nazionale in Florence Pan. 26. (Box 4, Folder 127)
    Con dolce brama [for three voices] -- Ogni dilletto [for two voices].
  - Praetorius, Michael, 1571-1621 Musae Sioniae, 5. T. In dulci jubilo (No. 81) In dulci jubilo: Mus. Sion V, Nr. 81 (1607), undated, 4 pages of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Pencil manuscript. Transcribed without text. (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Ripa, Alberto da, d. 1551 Fantasies, lute, no. 1 Fantasie: Albert de Rippe de Mantoue (1553): Liv. I, Fantas I (f. 1): F 2897, undated, 3 pages of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Ink manuscript. Incomplete transcription in keyboard format. From Ripa's Premier livre de tabulature da leut, contenant plusieurs chansons et fantasies (1553). At head of caption title: Abschriften aus Fleischer's Französ Abschriften (possible reference to Oskar Fleischer?). (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Rognoni Taeggio, Francesco Canzonas. Rigamonta Partito delle canzoni à 4 & 8 voci di Gio. Domenico Rognoni Taeggio, Milano 1605: La Rigamonta, Canzon 13, undated, 2 pages of manuscript music; 24 x 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcribed in keyboard format. (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Schmid, Bernhard, 1535-1592 Neue kunstliche Tabulatur. Alemando novelle Alemando novello: Ein guter neuer Dantz (Strassburg 1577), undated, 1 leaf of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Ink manuscript. (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Schmid, Bernhard, 1567-1625 Tabulatur Buch. No. 68. Selections Tabulaturbuch 1607 (Strassburg). No. 68: Fuga à 4 And. Gabr. (Fol NIIIv), undated, 1 leaf of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Incomplete: consists of first ten measures. Transcription in keyboard format from tablature of Number 68, Fuga quarta, by Andrea Gabrieli. (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Schumann, Robert, 1810-1856 Gedichte, op. 30. Hidalgo. English Der Hidalgo, op. 30, no. 3: comp 1840: orig. D major / R. Schumann; [text by] E. Geibel; Engl. by Lewis Novra, undated, 4 pages of manuscript music; 31 cm.; Ink manuscript. Vocal line only, with English text. It is incomplete. (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Sermisy, Claudin de, ca. 1490-1562 Content est riche en ce monde I Libro de le canzoni francese --- per Andrea Antigo intagliate. Venedig (O. Scotto) 1535, undated, 3 pages of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Two double-staved scores vertically aligned. The top score contains only the altus and bass voice parts of Sermisy's chanson with the text written beneath the top voice. This matches the copy in the Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich. The bottom score is the keyboard arrangement contained in Pierre Attaingnant's 1530 Paris publication, Vingt et six chansons musicales. Note in caption: Aus Beilage IV. Contained on pages 260-263 of Kinkeldey's Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts. (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Sperontes, 1705-1750 Singende Muse an der Pleisse. Selections Singende Muse an der Pleisse. Theil 1 No. 8, undated, 5 pages of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript with pencil emendations. The first two transcriptions include the first verse of related texts. (Box 4, Folder 135)
    [No. 8 Bourée] Ihr Grillen weicht, ihr Sorgen flieht -- [No. 9 Murki] Unter hunderttausend Schönen -- [No. 1 Air] [Ein edles Herz ist stets vernügt (two copies) -- [No. 6 Air allegro] [Alles, alles, hör' ich an].
  - Susato, Tielman, fl. 1529-1561 Danserye. Selections Three dances by Tielman Susato, undated, 4 pages of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. (Box 4, Folder 136)
    Bergerette: Antwerpen 1551 -- Danse du Roy: Antwerpen 1551 -- Saltarelle: Antwerpen 1551.
  - Thomas de Sancta Maria, fray, d. 1570 Arte de tan~er fantasi´a. Selections Arte de tan~er fantasi´a (1565), undated, 26 pages of manuscript music; 33-35 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcribed in keyboard format. Contained on pages 236-244 of Kinkeldey's Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts. (Box 4, Folder 137)
    Der erste modus (Fol 67v) -- Der zwierte modus (Fol 68) -- Der dritte modus (Ebenda) -- El quarto tono ... (Fol 68v) [crossed out version] -- Der vierte modus (Fol 68v) -- Der erste modus auf C (Fol 72v) -- Primero por gesolreut ([Fol 72v]) -- Die Harmoniesierung einer Melodie (Th. II Fol 32v) -- Vollstandige Harmonie-Wechsel (Fol 33) Oktavschritte im Bass (Ebenda) -- Wie man beim Fantasieren vorgeht (Th. II, Fol 120v) -- [Fantasie concierto] ([Th. II],Fol 121) -- Exemplo de unisonar a quatro semibreves por las compuestas ([Th. II], Fol 42) -- Exemplo de quando entra primero el contrabaxo (Th. II, Fol 73v) -- Quando el passo se haze en quarta ... (Th. II, Fol 74) -- [Quando el passo se haze quinta ...] ([Th. II], Fol 75) -- Exemplo de quando la voz del un duo ... ([Th. II], Fol 77) -- Exemplo de quando en lugar del segundo duo, se tañen a tres vozes con diversas consonancias ... ([Th. II], Fol 78) -- Exemplo de quando las mismas vozes que han concluydo el passo ... ([Th. II], Fol 79) -- Del modo de tañer los passos sueltos Cap. XXXV ([Th. II], Fol 79v) -- Arte de tañer (([Th. II], Fol 80) -- Del modo de asir un duo con otro sin clausula Cap. XXXVIII ([Th. II], Fol 82v) -- [Exemplo de todo lo sobre dicho] ([Th. II], Fol 83v) -- Del entrar las vozes medio copas antes dela clausula ([Th. II], Fol 90) -- Del entrar las vozes enel segundo lugar dela clausula ([Th. II], Fol 106) -- Primero del cesolfaut ([Th. I], Fol 72v) [two copies].
  - Trostlicher Liebe in seven versions, undated, 4 pages of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. Sources include compilations by Hans Gerle and Hans Newslider. (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Venetianische Opera Sinfonien. Abschriften von Kretzschmar, undated, 3 manuscript scores (16, [1], [5] pages); 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. Title from 16 page score. Possibly related to Hermann Kretzschmar's article, Die venetianische Oper und die Werke Cavallis und Cestis’ in Vierteljahrsschrift für Musikwissenschaft: viii (1892), 1–76. (Box 4, Folder 139)
    Score 1. Sinfonie zu Doriclea, 1645; Sinfonie zu Eligobalo, 1659; Ercole, 1662 / Fr. Cavalli ( Cavalli, Pier Francesco, 1602-1676) -- Il Tito, 1666; Argia, 1669. Prologue and Act I, scene 1 opening / M. A. Cesti ( Cesti, Antonio, 1623-1669) -- Marcello, 1670 / G. Ant. Boretti ( Boretti, Giovanni Antonio, ca. 1640-1672) -- Seleuco, 1666. Sinfonia and Act III, scene 15; Adelaide (Trompetenouverture), 1672 / M. A. Sartorio ( Sartorio, Antonio, 1630?-1681) -- Candaule, 1679 / PoA. Ziani ( Ziani, Pietro Andrea, 1616-1684).
    Score 2. Sinfonie avant opera Griselda (1721, Text Rusponi) [incomplete Presto movement] / A. Scarlatti ( Scarlatti, Alessandro, 1660-1725).
    Score 3. Sinfonie [complete three movement Sinfonia from the opera L'Amor volubile, e tiranno] / Scarlatti ( Scarlatti, Alessandro, 1660-1725).
  - Verovio, Simone, fl. 1575-1608 Diletto spirituale. Selections Diletto spirituale, Canzonette a tre a quattro voci composte de diversi eccmi. musici, Racolta da Simone Verovio ... Roma, 1586, undated, 4 pages of manuscript music; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Pages numbered 21-24. Contained on pages 280-282 of Kinkeldey's Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts. Accompanied by earlier draft (4 page ink manuscript). Accompanied by leaf marked Beilage V. (Box 4, Folder 140)
    Jesu decus angelicum / Felice Anerio -- Jesu mi dulcissime / Felix Anerius.
  - Vicentino, Nicola, 1511-ca. 1576 Antica musica ridotta alla moderna prattica. Dolce mio ben Essempio della prima parte di uno madrigale a quattro voci ..., undated, 2 pages of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. From Vicentino's Antica musica ridotta alla moderna prattica, Rome, A. Barre, 1555, Book III, Chapter 52, fol. 67v. Transcribed without accompanying words. (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Virdung, Sebastian, b. 1465? Musica getutscht. Sancta et immaculata virginita Aus Virdungs Musica getutscht, 1511. Sancta et immaculata virginitas ..., undated, 1 page of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcription in keyboard format. (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Warren, Samuel P. (Samuel Prowse), 1841-1915 Solomon's prayer Solomon's prayer (I Kings VIII): choir responses, undated, 4 manuscript music parts; 33 cm.; Ink manuscript. Parts (2 pages each) for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass. Slightly different from the same responses published in Selected readings for the church service, with choir responses (1909), with readings selected by James M. Ludlow and music by Samuel P. Warren. (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Unidentified Fanfares for brass and timpani, undated, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) and 8 manuscript instrumental parts; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. Parts for Tromba in C I, II, and II, Corno in F I and II (on one page), Trombone I and II (on one page), and Timpani. (Box 4, Folder 144)
    Seven short works for which only the trumpet parts contain all of the music.
  - Unidentified Tanz, undated, 1 page of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Scored for four unspecified instruments. Ink manuscript. (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Unidentified Tho I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not love, undated, 1 leaf of manuscript music; 27 x 25 cm.; Pencil manuscript. Fragment consisting chiefly of a single melody line in bass clef with text beneath it. Text from the Bible, Corinthians I:13. (Box 4, Folder 146)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Hanson, Howard, 1896-1981; Committee on Graduate Study in Music
Subjects
Musicologists; Music--Instruction and study--United States; Music in universities and colleges--United States; Musical notation; Kinkeldey, Otto, 1878-1966--Archives
Genres
Correspondence; Offprints; Scores
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Other Institutions
Otto Kinkeldey Papers, 1902-1966
14-20-1000
Cornell University's collection contains personal and professional papers, correspondence, teaching materials, and photographs.
Otto Kinkeldey Papers, 1908-1962
JPB 86-16
New York Public Library's collection contains personal and professional papers and correspondence.